this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software
Tommy butoh is principal site
reliability engineer at gremlin where
she works on chaos engineering prior to
that she worked at Dropbox inside
reliability engineering and also at
digitalocean in cloud infrastructure as
a service she's also co-founder of Girl
Geek Academy which is a global movement
to teach 1 million women technical
skills by 2025 Tommy welcome to the show
thanks very much I'm really excited to
be here
thank you today we're gonna be talking
about chaos engineering and I want to
begin with understanding the motivation
of it because what I saw is that some of
the worst outages are what led to the
introduction of chaos engineering you
worked at Dropbox can you talk about its
worst outage ever over there yeah sure
it's definitely true that a lot of the
worst outages that have happened a
number of companies have been resulted
in those companies deciding to start
practicing chaos engineering so the
worst outage at Dropbox is publicly
available on the blog it was in 2014 and
it went for multiple days so it was a
really bad outage related to the
databases and you can read about it the
VP of engineering wrote a full review of
what had happened and also explained the
action items that were going to be taken
to make sure that it wouldn't happen
again and one of those action items was
actually doing a lot of work to inject
failure to make sure that everything was
more reliable because it is this whole
new idea which is what chaos engineering
is
is that you can inject failure similar
to the idea of when you get a flu shot
you inject a bit of harm but it actually
makes you stronger and you're able to
withstand like really bad failure in the
future because you've injected it
frequently and yeah I just think chaos
engineering to me it's a it's just
something that you should be doing and a
lot of people learn it the hard way
mm-hmm I am really excited to be helping
people learn it before they have a very
very bad outage mm-hmm and just to
clarify yours what you're saying is
chaos engineering means injecting
failure yes okay and sort of the purpose
of this is to learn about what potential
potentially could go wrong is that
correct yeah so the idea is say for
example we all know these days that you
run on infrastructure whether it's bare
metal or if it's on the cloud you know
that it's gonna fail it's gonna break in
some way you might have hardware failure
power failure firmware failure some sort
of kernel issue some sort of issue with
your own tooling there can be so many
different types of things that go wrong
and it's just really common like we all
know that that things will go wrong
I think sometimes though we wish and
dream that cloud infrastructure was
going to be a hundred percent available
all the time and work perfectly but we
really know deep down that that's not
true and we need to build out
infrastructure with that in mind knowing
that things will break but then actually
it's much better if you control the
injection of failure so instead of
saying well like I know that maybe I'm
gonna have some downtime and my
infrastructure is going to break
maybe you think my only break once every
few months it's actually better to
inject the failure observe it monitor it
learn from it and also then make your
infrastructure more reliable because you
learn so much from actually doing chaos
engineering experiments so that's what I
really like to focus on if you think
about it like injecting failure to
do something simple like shut down an
instance or shut down a server that then
make sure that you're testing a number
of things like your automated
self-healing tooling that you may have
like hopefully you've got that there in
place or if you're say for example
shutting down regularly a replica for a
database then you're testing to make
sure that your clone process is really
resilient instead of only testing the
cloning process when a replica shuts
down because maybe that only happens
once every few months or maybe it
happens once every few weeks but if you
actually test it once a week on a
regular basis I think that's so much
better or even more frequently on once a
week you could really test it once a day
hmm
a lot of this depends on how big your
infrastructure is because say if you
have you know you have tens of thousands
of servers or thousands of servers or
hundreds of servers it really depends on
how frequently you're going to be
injecting failure and also what kind of
failure you'll inject but everybody can
learn from failure injection yeah it's
just so much better yes the first time
where I came into contact with the
notion of testing for failure and sort
of try to prevent failure was in the
testing discipline so I'm curious how it
differs from chaos engineering or does
differ at all yeah so for my background
I came up through studying computer
science working as a software engineer
then for me I started to work at a bank
after University and it was really
interesting for me because in a bank you
have to do something called disaster
recovery tests they call them deities
and you need to do them once a quarter
to hold your banking license it's a it's
a compliance requirement and if you
can't prove that you can fail over your
entire bank then you actually have
problems with the regulators and they
will say look we you need to be able to
prove this because otherwise you can't
hold your banking license you can't
service customers so then you'll be shut
down so that was where I was actually
introduced to this idea of large-scale
failover you actually failover
everything and you also
attesting that your entire team can
operate even if your office wasn't
available and it was the weekend so you
actually go to a different building for
two days over the weekend and fail over
everything and make sure that yeah if
something went wrong at your
headquarters you'd be able to use the
Internet you'd all have your laptops you
have everything required to be able to
keep the bank running during that
weekend hmm so that was my introduction
and then you know while I was working as
an engineer there I actually was doing a
lot of things I was very much full-stack
before it was called full stack and I
actually just really really wanted to go
further and further back into the stack
because I was feeling like when I was
building things you know the business
might come to me and say hey Tommy would
be really great if you could build a new
way for people to be able to process
mortgages maybe you could build a mobile
app or a new type of interface and I
just felt like whenever I build
something it was always really slow like
I couldn't rely on the infrastructure
that was underneath it for it to work
well so it actually sent me further and
further backwards I spent a lot of time
working with the database then I went
even further back to looking at the
hardware because it was all bare metal
at the time working with networking also
working on security as an engineer there
too and for me I learned yeah that you
know you really it is very helpful if
you have a good understanding from the
very top level of JavaScript like how
can your JavaScript fail how can your
CSS fail how can that actually impact
the user then all the way back down to
the power within the data center or that
your cloud infrastructure user your
provider is using so like going over it
through every single level that's where
you can actually think about failure
injection and you can inject it across
the whole stack like and I think of it
also like the OSI model thinking about
every layer there but the thing is what
I really learned over the years is if
you are doing failure injection right up
you know the hardware level that's going
to impact everything or the network
level so that's an area where I think we
need
do a lot of work to be able to withstand
those failures because you know if your
infrastructures down everything's down
you can't access anything whereas say
for example if you have your CSS is not
working like something's gone wrong
there then you might have changed the
way that you're like your interface is
presented to users or it might be
completely not in a functional State at
all depending on how you're using CSS so
it's really interesting when you look at
every single layer and that's how I
think about it but I didn't come from a
testing background except for just
having to perform disaster recovery
tests but I have worked with a lot of
teens that have done really great work
doing testing and they did a lot of
automated testing so I've worked really
closely with those teams and yeah that's
been really interesting within banking
when you have the automated testing
teams they're doing a lot of work to
make sure that everything is processed
correctly but yeah there's also a lot of
that's a whole nother field and industry
the space of testing yes and you
mentioned something just now disaster
recovery tests by this do you mean for
example what you mentioned at the
beginning where you said you're shutting
down a replica and you might want to
test yourself healing tool is that what
disaster recovery test means so disaster
recovery test is even bigger large-scale
more like scale than that so the idea
would be that you failover your entire
company so you shut down all of your
normal like business operations you shut
down the building even you shut down all
of your primary database primary data
center primary services and you failover
to usually they call it hot cold or
sometimes they do hot hot so you
actually failover to the cold often with
banking and it's that you actually have
like a full nother set of hardware in a
totally different data center that
you're able to bring up and get
everything running so every single
service would failover if it's like
foreign exchange mortgage broking
internet banking they'll go through
every service and make sure that all of
them work mm-hmm so essentially what
you're doing here is
you're testing the backup services right
the backup hardware and everything in
case the one you're currently using is
failing
exactly yeah like and the reason is you
do it often for preparing for a
large-scale not natural disaster that's
what a lot of people really worried
about so for example what if there was
an earthquake or something like that and
often your backup data center is usually
quite far away from where your primary
one is so that it should be far enough
that if there was some type of disaster
situation then you would be able to have
people that could go to that other
location that's what you really yeah I
see and earlier another thing you
mentioned was the infrastructure and the
size of the infrastructure how big it is
what is the role of this when deciding
whether to do chaos engineering or not
yeah like it's interesting if you think
of you know a very large-scale
infrastructure so let's say you have
infrastructure where there are over
let's say over 5,000 machines like
that's quite big and if you have
overthought five thousand machines but
say you only have like a few engineers
who are managing the maintenance the
operations
all of that sort of work for these
machines keeping them up-to-date keeping
the fleet healthy then maybe you only
have a handful of engineers doing that
for 5,000 toast maybe you have five
engineers well maybe you have ten
engineers like that would actually be a
lot or maybe you have all of your
engineers that work at the whole company
are responsible for doing that but then
you only actually have say 200 engineers
and 5000 machines so often what you
realize is you have a lot of machines
but you don't have that many people so
that's why you need to do a lot of
automation work and you need to really
understand the failure modes that you
can get yourselves in and the thing
there too is say you have 10 engineers
who are responsible for maintaining the
fleet making sure that your systems are
reliable looking after availability and
durability and you have a team of SRS
really responsible for that but the
thing is you know not all of them would
have been there for many years maybe
some of them have only been there a few
months maybe some of them have been
there one year or a few have been there
for four years maybe some of them just
started maybe somebody has been there
for a fuse and they just left with a lot
of knowledge so that's always something
you need to think about with this type
of large-scale infrastructure there's a
lot of knowledge that needs to be
transferred throughout the team so I
also think there's something there with
large-scale infrastructure usually don't
have that many more engineers than you
do for small scale infrastructure but
you have a lot more that you need to
look after and a lot more that you need
to understand so that's also another is
and that chaos engineering can be useful
because you can use the failure
injection as on-call training and it
helps you to be able to go okay if we
even if you just walk through it and run
a game-day which is this idea of having
10 to 15 engineers in a room together
talking through some scenarios that you
might run through where you would inject
failure in your infrastructure
you could whiteboard it up and go all
right if we injected failure at this
point you know infrastructure then we
would expect this and this to happen and
then you would actually say we expect
these to be the downstream impacts or
the cascading failure could look like
this but then you could say we feel
pretty confident that we could inject
this type of failure and everything
would be alright and then within the
game day you would actually inject that
and then see how it goes so it's your
hypothesis that you have I feel like we
can for example shut down this replica
for this database and the clone should
kick off and everything should be fine
and then within this period of time I
would be back to having a primary with
tube replicas mm-hmm so that you'd run
through but there might be others that
you go well we're not yet ready to run
through that scenario and actually
inject that failure because we need to
do these five things we need to fix our
remediation we need to fix other parts
of our infrastructure to make it more
reliable so that it can withstand that
failure and that's what you're going to
learn when you do these exercises so one
thing you mentioned is it's important to
have it in
depending on the nature of your
employees if they have been a long time
or not and also what you're saying is
there isn't really a rule that just says
chaos engineering should just happen if
you're operating at large scale you can
also do it at small scale right and it's
super important actually to do it at
small scale because one of the really
common mistakes I think running
small-scale infrastructure is having
like not enough machines and just
putting everything on you know maybe
three or four servers or instances and
not spreading things out not having
redundancy not having backups that's
like where you get into trouble because
you know you don't yet have a ton of
users so you don't need to have that for
the you know to be able to handle the
large amount of traffic but the thing is
if you don't have those backup
mechanisms in place and that redundancy
and you don't think about how you can
failover your services then it's
actually going to be impossible to be
able to failover and what you'll notice
will happen with really small scale
infrastructure when they haven't
invested in building that out is that
they can have like much longer downtime
and then much more at risk of data loss
because they haven't thought through the
backup scenario for their database
infrastructure for example maybe they
hope they've not tested the restore
process to see if they can actually
restore their backups and also they
often might not have very good incident
management programs in place to be able
to know yes like we're currently
experiencing issue we need to do this to
fix it but a lot of these things you
know it doesn't take a ton of time to
get set up and to put in place but you
need to think about it in a really
different way so a lot of the time it
actually comes down to funding because
you need to pay extra money to be able
to afford to purchase these instances
but that's the exciting thing about
cloud infrastructure now though it's
becoming more and more affordable and
you're able to purchase smaller size
instances
you can spread out your services across
a number of instances and then think
about building more reliable
infrastructure and understanding that
failure will happen and that's expected
but building our infrastructure to
handle them so that's why I'm excited
about right now use three much harder
you and you would have to buy bare metal
you could only afford one server or
maybe three servers and you know then
when they would fail you'd have to try
and get them repaired now it's totally
different with cloud infrastructure yes
and actually the first thing that I was
thinking about was this additional cost
like you're saying being available in
other countries having more in instances
cost money
so that's what I was wondering to what
extent is this lack of knowledge about
needing to have these things in place
and also the effect of cost on this but
it sounds like it shouldn't be a
significant cost no it's really not a
significant cost and then also you have
to look at you know the cost of servers
these days they're getting cheaper and
cheaper all the time like when you get
your instances then the other thing is
you look at the other side if you pay
for example this much for your
infrastructure this is your monthly bill
what would happen if you were down for
three days which is pretty common like
you can definitely you see quite
frequently three-day outages or even
week-long outages and these happen to
some of the biggest companies and you
know small companies as well it happens
to everybody and the thing there is here
what happens to your business if you're
down for three days your customers are
very unhappy and you might lose your
customers whereas if you think I'm going
to invest in my infrastructure but I'm
going to build it in a reliable way
which means I'm gonna build it in this
way that it might cost me a bit more for
my monthly bill but then that means I'm
gonna have a more reliable service and
my customers will be happier because
they're not going to experience that
downtime like day loss which is even
worse mm-hmm and I guess also the nature
of the product and the project matters
because for example if it's a photo app
maybe it's not that critic
you're not gonna lose customers they're
just gonna be annoyed like ah doesn't
work today
but if you're dealing with a hospital
system or a banking system I think it's
even more critical right the type of
data yeah definitely it's really
interesting like I think other way that
I think about it too is even if it was a
photo app because people can so easily
move services if your photo app is down
and somebody trusted their photos in
there and then it goes down for a day or
two days and they can't access their
photos then they might lose trust right
in your business because they feel like
can i really trust my photos in there do
I need to have a backup service to hold
another set of my photos then why am I
paying for this service if I don't trust
it
I couldn't even access my own data and
then they might worry that if it was
down does that mean that it's not
reliable that one day it might lose data
so I think like these are all the things
that people think about right when
they're looking at whether they want to
use a service and that's like that's a
tough spot to be in when it's so easy
for people to create new businesses
these days and I just think it's worth
it then you know I actually feel like
building more reliable services can
actually help you acquire new customers
and can help you make money because
you're showing people that they can
trust your service that's true and also
like you said even the big players the
big companies have had outages for
several days sometimes but what's good
is that these companies make available
their infrastructure like AWS where I
where I assume they put all those
learnings and you are more equipped to
recover from failure if you leverage
their systems right yeah exactly like
it's often um like for example there was
a big outage last year that I was
uncalled-for which was the s3 outage and
the thing no it was it was a region of
s3 that was impacted and there are
several regions that you can use or you
can have a backup mechanism in place so
that if that region goes down then you
have some type of failover ready and I
think that's just a really important way
that we need to think these days yeah
yeah I want to talk in more detail about
chaos engineering
the types of failures that we can
discover by using it can you talk about
some examples of things we can find find
out by using chaos engineering yeah sure
so just last week I actually taught at
chaos engineering boot camp which was at
SR econ in Santa Clara and during that
boot camp it's a half day boot camp I've
done it twice now I also did it a Riley
velocity and it's really good experience
for engineers to come together what we
do is I create a cluster for everyone
because often people say oh is the only
way to learn about chaos engineering is
is it the only way to do it on
production and I always say no you can
actually start doing chaos engineering
first on just a demo environment then
you can also do it on stage and then
once you feel confident you can do it on
production but what I do for the chaos
engineering boot camp is create a demo
environment so I spin up a primary and
two nodes at kubernetes cluster for
everybody that's coming along and I
actually put people in groups I'll have
three people working on a cluster
together and then I give them access to
my github repo which has a few chaos
engineering experiments in there that
people can start to run which is like a
nice taste test for how do you start to
inject failure and how do you start to
run these different types of experiments
and I also deploy a demo microservices
app from we've works which is an
ecommerce store so it means that when
you come into the workshop you've got
this demo environment you have the
application there you can go to the IP
address you can see the e-commerce site
running and then you can start to inject
the failure but because you've got three
people that have access to the cluster
it's really much more interesting
they're having just one person on that
demo environment because it's it's more
similar to actually working on
production systems where you have
multiple people that have access to your
infrastructure at the same time right
and like this actually teaches you a lot
about running chaos engineering
experiment in a safe way and in a secure
way because there are a lot of ways that
you can do it badly so I like to also
show people that side of
Engineering to that it's really
important to think of how you can run
these experiments in a safe way in a
controlled way instead of just random
and anyone doing whatever at any time so
the first experiment we do is a CPU
attack where we're just consuming CPU
resources and then that one shows you
what that looks like within your
infrastructure and I get people to check
like can you tell that it's happening
right now
I usually also put data dog agents on
there so then everyone can see what that
looks like but then you can also just
check from your command-line tools like
using H top or something like that and
and and yeah so you can actually then
see when you open up H top you can go
all right I can see the attack happening
right now I can see that it's consuming
CPU resources but then you'll see how
does kubernetes handle this and for that
attack that specific one it everything's
pretty good and you know nothing strange
you'll notice nothing really that is
customer impacting but then we around
some other attacks which are much more
damaging so we run a network corruption
attack
we're actually corrupting Network
packets and I and for this workshop was
very interesting like usually you would
corrupt a smaller percentage of packets
but I decided to go wild and my script
was corrupting 50% of packets because I
just wanted to make it that you could
really see the impact of the chaos
engineering experiment and you
definitely could so especially on
conference Wi-Fi when people started to
run that it just like completely hose
their instances they're able to see what
happens when you have a massive network
issue where there's like high amount of
packet corruption and then like you
can't actually load the site you can't
even load top you know you're not able
to actually see what's happening on your
hosts at all so that's at a point where
if you had automated remediation and
automated tooling then you would because
you've got this kubernetes cluster like
the idea there is you would be able to
just get rid of that host and then have
a new host replace it which I like that
about kubernetes that it's built in a
way that you should be able to just get
rid of hosts because something weird is
going on on that host and that is a way
to actually trigger that to happen
because you're causing some type of
failure that is not expected right but
then you need to be able to capture that
record that and make it understand that
it means that your system needs to take
an action based on that so yeah that's
like two examples of the attacks there
are so many others another one is you
know you can do DNS related attacks
often there was like a big dying outage
that happened then you can also do
blackhole attacks time travel all types
of different attacks we have 11 attacks
per book built into gremlin and we just
launched in December so that's really
exciting and we're constantly building
more creating more different ways to
inject value in unique ways because I
think everyone thinks of failure as a
host going down but that's just pretty
standard failure we're trying to think
more about the weird types of failure
say for example if you inject network
latency to a replica for a database what
happens to the primary when it's trying
to communicate with the replicas can it
handle that does something go wrong with
the replication process what happens if
a promotion then needs to happen so it
enables you to actually think through
all of these things and then actually
trigger the failure to understand what
happens you mentioned a couple of
interesting points over here especially
the attacks one thing that I wanted to
clarify regarding the test experiment
and the setup is you mentioned you you
added a couple of data dog agents can
you explain what this is yeah so data
dog is a monitoring tool and you can
deploy your agent in different ways so
you can just install it directly on the
host or you can you can do it in a
number of different ways and and it's a
it's you're able to get a free trial for
data dog so that's why I like to use it
because it's um it's very quick so you
install the agent just run one simple
line script and then your agent will
then start reporting data to the data
dog UI and you're able to pick up all
the stuff like CPU resources all the
things that we need to know for when
we're running our attacks and I find
that to be a really handy way to show
everyone very very quickly on a demo
environment what the impact is
failure injection because it's very
visible but if you didn't want to use
data dog then you could use something
else like Prometheus and graph honor and
use some open source monitoring tools
like that but yeah the way that gremlin
works is actually similar to the idea of
how you would install data dog to so if
a gremlin to Chaos engineering
experiments you actually also install an
agent on every host or you can install
gremlin inside a container and yeah
that's how that works - so similar idea
where you have agents across your hosts
and then you report back up and then
also there's like a control plane with a
nice UI and API and a command line tool
as work become synonymous with email do
you hear chat pings in your sleep good
news Stack Overflow for teams is a
private secure home for your teams
questions and answers and more digging
through stale wiki's and lost emails
give your team back the time it needs to
build better products go to STK slash
radio to try teams today with your first
14 days free yes since you just brought
up gremlin and it's where you're
currently working can you explain a
little bit more about what it is yeah so
gremlin is the first company founded to
actually provide a platform to do chaos
engineering and it's like a hundred
percent focused on doing that so I was
really excited to join I joined at the
end of last year and I met the founders
a few years back when I was I just
started working at Dropbox and one of
the founders Colton he's the CEO he
reached out to me and asked me if I'd
like to speak on a conference track that
he was putting together for cuke on New
York and he was putting together a track
all about failure and he asked me if I
wanted to speak about disaster recovery
testing that I was running at Dropbox
and what I'd done in the past it no but
it's like yeah that'd be great so that's
how we met
and we stayed in touch over the years
and then I reached out to him recently
because I was really interested in
working on gremlin with him and with the
team and I joined as employee 9 which is
very exciting to be working some ways
the smallest company
that I've worked out so far but I think
it's really great that we're actually
focused on building a chaos engineering
platform and we're trying to build it in
a way that it works for everybody
doesn't matter what infrastructure
you're using if you're on AWS if you're
on GC P as you are like it will work for
all of those different types of
platforms digitalocean their mat or
whatever it is and also whatever type of
infrastructure using if it's a if any
type of database my sequel Postgres
dynamodb it can be anything so to me
that's really exciting and a big step
forward for the industry because before
a lot of what was happening in the chaos
engineering space was that people were
you know making a lot of smaller tools
but they were focused on just doing one
type of thing just for one type of
provider or like just for one type of
experiment and there wasn't so much
where it was about let's build something
that actually works everywhere that's
what I really like the idea of doing
mm-hmm and does this include a set of
predefined tests that you can do yeah
exactly so we have a set of predefined
we call them attacks because we like to
say that you're actually triggering an
attack on your services or your
infrastructure and the idea too is like
if you talk to the netflix team that
they won't call them tests but colton
will talk about chaos engineering is
doing testing so different people have
different thoughts on that and what that
is and the reason they don't call it
test is because they say it's an
experiment so for a test you're trying
to test something I want to test this
and see the result with an experiment
it's more exploratory like you're trying
to learn from it so I guess that's like
one difference there but then we call
them attacks and I like to think of them
also is there's not only the predefined
attacks but you can also run attack
combos so you can combine several
attacks together and then see what is
the impact if you do say two attacks at
the same time how does your
infrastructure handle that that's when
you get to a really much more advanced
state you can also schedule the attacks
to run it at the same time every week on
the same day or you could schedule on
the run
or weekly so I think that's a really
good move forward as well
and there's also an API so you can
actually roll the attacks and gremlin
tooling into your own tooling so you can
make it very very easy to trigger
attacks based on something happening
within your own infrastructure or making
it easy that's something that Twilio did
recently which was pretty cool for one
of their systems called r8q so they use
the gremlin API to trigger failover yeah
in the workshop that you described that
you were giving about chaos engineering
you mentioned you did a couple of
attacks you and the people at the
workshop one of them was DNS related
there was another one called the black
hole attack
can you explain what this attack means
yeah so actually in the workshop I don't
do black hole Oh Dana I just do CPU and
network related attacks so you can find
those on my gear up if you go to
github.com slash tammy beautto you'll
find a reaper which is a chaos
engineering bootcamp repo and then when
within there I have some chaos and
engineering scripts that you can run so
you can just like pull that repo down
onto your machine and run those attacks
and then see the example of what happens
but then I we have some other types of
attacks that you can run as well which
are only available within gremlin yeah
those ones you have to actually get a
gremlin trial you can get a free trial
and you can check them out so with black
hole attack this attack will drop
matching network traffic that you
specify so that's what that idea is I
guess if you think about it like you're
creating a black hole and you're sending
all of the traffic into this black hole
so it's going to place basically nowhere
you're just black holing traffic then
DNS will block access to DNS service so
this is to be able to say well what
happens if our DNS servers were down
like say if you were using din and then
Dean had an outage like dying sorry what
would happen next and that's the idea
there yeah so and it's also a time
travel where you're actually changing
the system
for the hosts and that one is really
interesting like you think about it it's
similar to daylight savings maybe some
type of issue there or other time
related events like everyone was really
worried back in the day about like y2k
bug what happens when the time changes
and so you'd actually be able to
reproduce that for those that are not
familiar with the y2k bug can you
explain briefly what it is yeah it was
before I was working in industry so I
was in university I think it was like
when I was the year 2000 and then all of
them computers machines were going to
change like I was in high school at the
time
and it was like the y2k bug or the
millennium bug and everyone was really
worried like it was so interesting when
you read on the news everyone was
worried that all the computers in the
world were gonna crash and we would lose
all of the data everywhere and no one
would be able to access anything because
of how people had been storing time and
that they didn't think we'd be able to
handle when it cocked over and it was
2000 and they thought I might start
again from the beginning of time for
computers but actually in the end
everything was fine so it was really
like a big scare people were very
worried but in the end yeah it really
like wasn't a big issue but it was an
interesting thing and it could have
caused a lot of problems for people and
I think you know yeah it's an
interesting thing to read about yes
another thing that I wanted to clarify
is you're saying this attacks people can
find the scripts on your github can you
talk about these scripts like what are
they written in what do they look like
yep so if you check out my github you'll
find the scripts like they're actually
on my github they just bash scripts so
you can just run those but the other
thing is you don't have to run them as
bash scripts what you can do is one of
them you could just copy the command and
run it straight in your terminal and a
lot of the time like with chaos
engineering you know you're really using
you're using different types of things
that have been built into Linux that
you're trying to change or use to the
to introduce these values and these are
because their infrastructure related
failures like especially the networking
related ones so I would recommend just
like grabbing the script checking it out
first like read the script see how it
works you can read like the Linux manual
pages to see more learn more about what
I'm doing but it's actually really cool
to just run it yourself and you'll be
able to see the impact of those yeah
it's a really cool thing to do on a demo
machine if you you can even just do it
on a host with nothing else installed on
it if you've never run a Kaos
engineering experiment before and you'll
see like how easy it is to run your very
first experiment and that's something
that I'm really excited about is getting
everyone to be able to be today like
I've run my first Chaos engineering
experiment I injected failure I was able
to see the impact of it and that's why
I've got those up there so everyone can
get their first taste test before they
then move on and start to do it in stage
and then start to do it in production
and actually save the real value from
doing failure injection for real on real
services and actually triggering proper
failover and other types of actions that
you want your systems to take place so
this is like a hello world of case
engineering yeah that's actually what I
call it when I do the workshop I say
like this is the hello world of chaos
engineering it's like the real like you
know a good place has got it's a really
nice place to stop okay and earlier we
talked about experiments and attacks
these some people call it attacks like
you at gremlin other people call it
experiments but what essentially are the
results and how are they collected yeah
so it's actually a really interesting if
you use gremlin and what happens is you
trigger an attack we actually log the
progress of the attack and we think that
it's really important for your entire
team to know what attacks are happening
when so you can actually see that within
the UI you can see the history of all
attacks that have been run through their
run by what time they run what hosts
they were targeting what tags those
hosts had or instances and or containers
and so I think that's really important
because one of the big things with chaos
and
you need to make it very visible you
need to let people know what's happening
when because what happens if you trigger
some type of attack and it does
something unexpected and somebody didn't
know that the chaos engineering was
happening then they're going to be
really shocked right because they'll not
be expecting this to happen and you
don't want that you don't want chaos
engineering to be like that it's
actually better if you let people know
and you say hey like we're going to run
these chaos engineering experiments
they're controlled experiments we're
picking these services to run them on or
these containers these these instances
and then you actually let people know so
I also recommend creating a slack
channel if you use slack chaos
engineering slack channel and
automatically posting in there we
actually have a slack integration for
gremlin which is really cool so yeah
just automatically post in there and it
would say the attack has started now the
attack has been successful or sometimes
something could happen where the attack
might fail so then you'd also want to
know that why did the attack fail and
you can look into that so that's really
how that works and I think that that's
pretty important and how does the
organization learn from the results of
these experiments yeah so the big thing
that I think is important to do is you
need to have a few things in place first
before you start running your chaos
engineering experiment so that you can
make the most of them and really learn
so first off I like to start by saying
what you shouldn't do so what you
shouldn't do is like just have someone
decide to go in tomorrow and start
taking down services or totte start
taking down hosts and not telling anyone
because that's just like creating
unnecessary confusion and it's not
controlled chaos it's not in this spirit
of helping everyone learn together and
work together and get value from it it's
just like creating chaos in an
unnecessary way and also it's it's not
good to scare people and say hey like
we're gonna take down the whole data
center tomorrow like your service better
be ready and then the service teams go
what I'm not ready for that like you
can't just do that we'll have some
really big outages that's also not a
good thing too because chaos engineering
to me is it's definitely a journey so
you really need to get everybody on
board and treat it like a journey like
marathon that you're all going on
together or even more than a marathon
it's like an epic track because it's
going to take a long time and you need
to walk together and make sure that
you're already there and on the same
page yeah the next thing you want to do
is have a few things in place so it's
really important to have make sure that
you feel pretty confident with your
monitoring tooling so that if you were
below SLA for example your service level
agreement say that's 99.99 you'd be able
to know and I think a good question to
ask yourself is do you have one
dashboard that your entire company could
look at to know if you were currently
needing the SLA for your core products
that will a critical customer facing
products then the next question is do
you know what your five to ten critical
services are that your customers are
using are you able to list those out
like often one of them would be the
database another one might be say the
traffic services like if that's engine
acts or Apache and depending on your
business they would be there would be
other types of services too so it's
important to be able to know what those
are and then make sure that your
monitoring would bubble up that and I
recently wrote a post going through how
to create a high severity incident
management program which is on the
gremlin community and I really recommend
reading that as well to make sure that
you feel like you have a good incident
management program before you start to
do chaos engineering and the reason is
you know what happens if you run some
type of experiment and it causes an
outage but you don't have a high
severity incident management program and
you don't have a way to quickly escalate
issues to triage issues to make sort
make sure that they get resolved really
fast because I think it's important to
have that in place before you do chaos
engineering and it doesn't take a ton of
time to put something like that in place
you know you can really start to put
that in place within a week you can do
something like how volunteers who say
hey like I'm happy to be on-call to help
do this but I think it's a good thing to
really read through that because it's
quite detailed I think it's about 4,000
words but I really try to explain how to
build one of those programs aren't so
yeah monitoring is important before you
get started
you're critical services are is
important and then also making sure that
you have a high severity and management
program is important to mm-hmm
are coming up with these things and
defining these things what you call the
service level agreement yeah okay and
what was the name of that blog post that
you recommended yep it's called how to
establish a high severity incident
management program so it pretty long
title but if you look up my name like
Tammy judo gremlin and then look up
incident management or high severity
then you'll be able to find it when
doing these experiments and attacks
under the chaos engineering umbrella do
these normally happen during business
hours yes definitely yeah so when you
start they definitely happen during
business hours and I think that's really
important because the idea there is you
know you're coming together you're
running things purposely in a controlled
way often you might even start with
everybody in the same room when you're
running your first experiments that's
definitely what I did when I was working
at Dropbox when I would run the chaos
engineering experiments for the
databases I would be in a room I would
run through my different experiments and
I would have a few other engineers there
from the database's team when we take
turns like some weeks it would be my
turn to run them other weeks it would be
someone else and we were constantly
thinking of new experiments that we
wanted to run to so the thing there is
you know you'll run the same experiments
over and over and then it's good to
automate those and say ok like we've run
this many many times we're really
confident with the actions that happen
afterwards now we're just going to
automate that and then you could
actually have it happen at night time
outside of hours when everybody is
asleep but at the start it's good to do
it with everyone in the same room I do
think that that's really good and then
you start to think ok what happens what
are some other types of experiments we
could run and as a team you can
brainstorm those and you can say well
what happened like what would be really
bad if this happened it would be really
bad and then you actually write those
experiments out we would just write them
out on a white boy first
like let's actually think if this
happened that could be quite dangerous
for us it would be quite bad and then
actually go how can we make
so it wouldn't be so dangerous and make
your infrastructure and services more
resilient so they could handle that
failure scenario and then actually run
it so then that's a very good way to do
chaos engineering but often like we
talked about at the start
people do chaos engineering because
they've had some type of major outage or
massive you know catastrophic failure
and then they start to introduce chaos
engineering and that is a good way to
start so if you have an outage one of
the action items for the outage could be
do the fixes and then run actually
reproduce that outage again to make sure
that if it ever happened again you'd be
totally fine and you'd know that
everything was okay and your
infrastructure could handle it but then
you start to get into the space where
you're actually being more proactive
which i think is really cool but it
takes time it takes a few months to get
there for defining these attacks is
there a dedicated chaos team made up of
people that build the system or that
didn't build a system yeah like every
company seems to do it differently so
it's interesting I think um I've worked
at places where there's been a dedicated
team who thinks of what types of
situations to run most of the places
I've worked there are SRS who are
embedded on the teams that think about
what those experiments might be and then
they're the ones that usually guide the
like the brainstorming of what types of
experiments you write run but then
really the whole service team would have
input and we try and figure out what
types of experiments to run together but
I do think that it's really good to have
service teams own the experiments that
they're gonna run and the idea there is
that they know their service really well
right and they're constantly modifying
their service they're trying to make it
better they're adding new features when
they are new features then they might
also be new failure modes that can crop
up so it's really good for them to own
that I think and that's really important
but yeah there are a few companies where
they have a centralized chaos team that
would earn that initiative and to roll
it out across the company like Netflix
has a dedicated chaos team where they
would go across the company
evangelist and advocate for cows
engineering across the service teams so
that's a different approach that you can
do to and I think all approaches really
work but often it's either a chaos
engineer that that's their real gusset
title and they're the ones that do the
cows engineering or it could be an SRE
that does chaos engineering or Facebook
for example you're called a production
engineer so it might be production
engineers that do chaos engineering or
it could be sweet like a software
engineer that's really that really wants
to build reliable systems totally
understands that it's important wants to
make sure that what they build is
reliable so they'll be the ones that
decide to drive forward with injecting
failure and using chaos engineering as a
practice and this can also depend on the
resources of the organization in the
size of the organization right yeah like
the big thing is you know to start doing
chaos engineering it really only takes
one engineer so you don't have to have a
ton of people that are driving that
forward you can start small and we
really recommend that at gremlin as well
we talked about this idea of the blast
radius so it's important to start small
first run one small you know controlled
experiment on one service then gradually
expand out and like it's okay to start
and stage you don't have to start in
production then gradually do more and
more and I was like you start to show
the value and the benefit of chaos
engineering then you'll see more and
more people start to pick it up that
always happens and the other thing too
is to be able to show the value of chaos
engineering it's really important to
collect metrics to tell the story before
you start to do the chaos engineering
and then after and some examples of
metrics that you would want to collect
are incident counts so when I when I say
incidents I mean not just um like high
severity incidents but also alerts so
it's really important to collect if you
have something new something like page
duty you can have all of your alerts
that are in page duty and go all right
in the last week we had X hundred alerts
that actually paged an engineer and then
we then you can say we started to
introduce chaos engineering and we
actually had a reduction
say there was a 20% reduction in a month
of chaos engineering and then make of
them alerts because of the chaos
engineering and you could also say we're
tracking high severity outages so that's
why you'd want to have your high
severity incident management program and
you could say for example the worst type
of outages are Sub Zero which is a
catastrophic outage and maybe you were
having those quite frequently before you
started to do chaos engineering but then
you would be able to use the chaos
engineering to reduce your high severity
outages and what will often happen this
has been in my experience is you'll have
less very very catastrophic outages like
the really bad outages that Essebsi row
7 1 and you might have more outages
which has 7 to 7 3 so they don't impact
as customers as badly and that's pretty
common
mm-hmm and earlier we were talking about
this service level agreement and like
you said one of the main components of
this is monitoring and just now you're
mentioning keeping track of the number
of incident counts tracking the severity
of the outages is there anything else
that you recommend to having place under
mean yeah like the other thing you want
to do is collect as much data as you can
about your high severity outages because
really you shouldn't be having too many
of those but if you read my post on how
to set a program you'll see how to how
to measure those how to track those but
when you do start to capture the data on
those big incidents its high severity
incidents what you want to do is capture
the time to detection so how long did it
take you to actually detect the incident
was occurring the time to resolution how
long did it take you to fix that
incident and then also the time to
prevention how long did it take you from
fixing the incident to then doing all
the action items to try and say like we
we want to make this incident never
happen again
and then also running your game day and
your chaos engineering experiments to
confirm that your fixes have actually
worked because you know it's one thing
to like do fixes afternoon to know
to actually dukale's engineering and
reproduce the incident and prove that if
that happened again your infrastructure
would be totally fine and then the next
metric is the time between failures so
what you want to be measuring there is
if the incident actually did happen
again how long does it take for it to
happen again is it a week is it a month
is it six months so it's really good to
just be tracking those metrics - in
addition to measuring things related to
the incidents themselves and the time
between the failures do we also need to
be measuring for example CPU usage or
disk hundreds I actually some people
will say that you shouldn't measure
those things I think you should and a
lot of the time it comes for free out of
the box if you use a tool like data dog
they're going to help you easily measure
CPU disk i/o memory like that that comes
out of the box and the thing there is I
would say you want to be measuring it
and you also want to be looking at
things like measuring SAV got 10,000
hosts one of the handy things is to
measure CPU usage across all of your
hosts and look for spikes is there like
one host that's acting out and then it
seems unusual or strange and we would
often like in the past where I've worked
who would always alert on types of
issues where it goes above like 80%
because that some sort of issue is
happening you know that's unexpected and
I think if you feel like with your
infrastructure that it would be too
noisy to page for those things and I
think it's important to think about how
can you make your infrastructure more
reliable because you're really like
playing with fire there if you're
letting things get to a point where they
could just get knocked over because they
were consuming too many resources and
you're not handling that properly what
is the process of correlating an
incident and what happened for example
do you recommend looking at graphs of
what was the CPU would like and then
maybe there's some correlation there
yeah I really
so like the way that I do incident
like I think it's very important to have
two things one is an incident manager on
call which is a rotation of people who
are usually engineering leaders that
have quite a lot of experience managing
incidents and so I was an incident
manager on call at Dropbox while I work
there and you really on call over every
single service across the whole company
so if there's any type of major outage
that impacts Dropbox and you're going
and get paged if you're on call in it's
a 24/7 on-call rotation with yeah small
number of people five people or so and
the thing there is I think that's
actually really important to have that
rotation because those people like
they've had experience with managing
lives scale incidents before really good
skills and troubleshooting debugging
thinking fast being able to make sure
that they've got the right people there
to resolve the issue and it also means
that you're separating out the idea of
managing the incident and then resolving
the incident and to resolve the incident
it's really good to have a technical
lead on call this would be actually the
person who's on call for the service
that is currently having some type of
issue but the thing that a incident
manager is really good at is figuring
out which services are having an issue
and then there yeah you need to have a
really good high level dashboard that
shows you are we currently meeting SLA
and in that dashboard it's good to be
able to show this is the this is the
health of dub-dub job this is the health
of your API and then seeing if it's
below SLA or not and it's really clear
and easy to then see and then you go the
next level under after that that's what
I like to look at you can then have
other dashboards that show you your
critical services and you can quickly
pinpoint which services are having an
issue if you know what your critical
services are because usually it's one of
those if it's going to be impacting
users in a really big way it's usually
some type of critical service that's
having trouble and then you make sure
that because what can happen to is say a
critical service has just deployed
something new or some type of issue has
occurred that's impacted that critical
service but maybe they might not even
catch it with their own alerting that
they've built for their service it might
be something that slips past them but
the thing is if you have internet
managers
call then they're going to get paged for
drops in SLA so they're actually looking
at it from the customer perspective not
from the service perspective and their
job is to just fix stuff they're just
trying to get everything back up and
running as soon as possible and they
make sure that they find the right
service team that needs to fix it and
they get the right people on board
so yeah this you're only too many things
to be able to triage but you do need to
know like what is our SLA right now are
we meeting it what are our critical
services which ones are having an issue
majority the time it's going to be one
of those that is actually having an
issue it's pretty rare that you have a
customer facing impact and it's
something really small and obscure
sometimes that can happen and it's
harder to debug and that's when you see
like the mean time to detection of what
the actual incident is taking a really
long time and then you need to be able
to have much better diagnostic tools so
yeah but this is like you know after
after doing incident management for a
really long time you just get really
fast at it and it's a skill that you
develop you mentioned an important thing
is to have incident management in place
which means to have at least one person
on call and this person has really good
debugging skills knows the system really
well how can you start training other
employees so you don't always rely on
the senior more senior people on the
team can you do that I think like the
big thing there is you don't want to
have to me it's like you don't want too
many cooks in the kitchen so the thing
there is you actually want pretty small
rotations for those incident management
rotations having five people where they
sink once a week they make sure they
understand which new services are being
built which new teams have been created
because they need to have a good
understanding of the services that exist
but also the teams and the engineers
that are working on the teams and that's
you know that can be quite hard if
there's like several hundred engineers
and it becomes like part of your role
and your job of what you do day-to-day
is that you need to keep up with what's
happening across the company so you're
always aware and understand what's going
on but I think then it's actually a
really good opportunity for some
if they really want to learn to be good
at that so be really good at incident
management they could just put their
hand up and say hey like I'm interested
in this being part of my career path
going forward I'd really like to become
good at this it's a skill that I'd like
to develop and then they should really
do some training so what you can do
there is they could shadow an incident
manager on call they could get the pages
UT alerts at the same time as the
incident manager and then jump online as
soon as that incident manager is working
on the incidents they could jump online
right with them and then just shadow
them by watching what they do and the
best way to learn often with that is
just by watching it helps even more if
they're able to sit by them in the
office if it's a daytime page but it
could be in the middle of the night and
that's how you really learn and for me I
started to do the high severity incident
management work really early in my
career and it was actually just because
you know nobody wanted to do it and I
thought well it's pretty important I
actually really care that when I'm
building services and software I want
people to be able to use it and I want
people to have a good experience using
it so I felt like it was something that
I just wanted to learn I wanted to be
really good at and I wanted to reduce
the amount of incense we were having I
wanted to reduce the amount of time it
took to resolve incense I wanted to
reduce just the impact to people that
were using our software and I've learned
a lot of these doing it so I definitely
recommend that it's a very good thing to
learn it's a great skill to develop and
it also is a really great skill for your
life outside of work because you're able
to manage these you know high impact Jai
can be high stress moments where
sometimes they can take several hours
like the s3 outage last year I was on
call there and working on that for you
know five hours straight so you have to
be very very good very focused for
sometimes several hours until it's
resolved but yeah I think it's a good
thing to do yes and it can also help on
other type of skills like you said how
are you reacting to this failure you're
having anxiety or things like that right
exactly like you learn how to be
really calm and like my friends who
always tell me outside of work if like
any type of issue happens I'm so good at
figuring out how to resolve things so
often my friends will say oh like you
know I had this issue I just lost my
passport I mean this random country what
do I do
really good at being able to think
through like these are the types of
different actions that you need to take
to be able to resolve this as soon as
possible you just get really good at
that and that's a great life skill and
then you hide your friends past for us
to inject chaos in their lives or
something
[Laughter]
well Tommy thank you for taking the time
to come on the show it's been a pleasure
talking with you about chaos engineering
thank you so much it's been really great
to talk to you too for a software
engineering radio this is Elena Salinas
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by
Archer police software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening